The following content is
provided under a Creative
Commons license. .
Your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue
to offer high quality
educational resources for free.
To make a donation or
view additional materials
from hundreds of MIT courses,
visit MIT OpenCourseWare
at ocw.mit.edu.
PROFESSOR 1: We've
revised 1805, and MIT five
is the introductory
probability and statistics
class for mostly
non-math majors.
For most of them, it's the
only probability and statistics
class they'll take.
A lot of them will
go on to be doctors
and so our goal is to have
at least statistically
literate doctors out there.
That's important.
Now let's keep it back there.
We've been supported
for two years
by a Davis Foundation grant.
The PI on the grant
is Haynes Miller.
And I classify him as
our PI and visionary,
because the vision of bringing
active learning into the math
department was his, and
it takes some effort.
So thank you for that, and
it's working in some way.
You'll see.
Here's the outline of the talk.
We'll talk about
what we inherited,
but we came into with
1805, what we've done,
and what we've learned.
And along the way, we'll
do a little demonstration.
So what we found when we,
what the state of 1805
three years ago, was it was
a traditional lecture class
taught at MIT as a lecture
with a recitation component.
And the enrollment
was dwindling.
Students were not taking it.
They've migrated
to another class.
Part of it was that the
faculty who were teaching it
we're not-- how do I
say it gently-- were not
so interested in this section
of undergraduate education.
And in fact the year
we took it over,
I think we were faced--
Haynes can correct me
if I'm wrong-- with the
choice of either us taking it
over or not teaching the class.
So the first year we did
teach it as a lecture class.
John was a recitation
instructor.
I was a lecture.
And then in the
next two years we
converted to a fully flipped
classroom active learning
and we co-teach it.
So what we found is just that.
Haynes had a big interest
in active learning,
he's been pushing
them in recitations
for years with some success I
would say now, it's built up,
and Davis and everyone is
interested in the world
of online learning and
what can happen there.
So we have a component
of the class online.
The class itself will
be put on OpenCourseWare
educator at the
end of this year.
So what did we do?
We changed everything at once.
In retrospect, I would
say I don't recommend it.
But having gotten
through it, you're
always glad that you did it
all at once, because now we
don't have to do
any of these pieces.
We can just keep refining them.
It's a lot to talk
about, so we're not
going to focus much
on the new curriculum.
I'll just say a few words, that
we're really of The curriculum
that we have.
We've introduced a unit
on Bayesian inference.
[INAUDIBLE] here is our
Bayesian, Can I say zealot?
Does is say that's your
religion on your Facebook site?
PROFESSOR 2: No.
That's me.
PROFESSOR 1: Oh, that's John.
That's on John's site.
John is a convert.
Bayesian unit.
What that has done
for us is allows
us to bridge the gap between
the probability and statistics
part, which is
always a hard gap.
Probability I'll say is
a mathematical science.
Statistic is that
statistics are at least as
much art as science.
And so I was to bridge that,
Bayesian inference and Bayesian
learning are becoming more
and more important today.
So it's good that they see it.
And finally, even
if they're just
doctors who need to
know what P value is,
we feel we can explain
the P value better
by having introduced this unit.
So actually added three weeks
worth of material to the class,
and we'll talk a little
bit about that later.
Then we'll speak more
about the pedagogy,
the importance of the
classroom, and what technology
we have in the class.
And now we actually
we're going to show you--
this is a video-- a little bit,
where you should pay attention
while you're
watching the video is
the energy in the classroom
and particularly the comments
and the oohs and ahs that come
at the end when you'll see John
talking some students on this.
Today we're going to do
Bayesian updating, which
is to say we're going to
be using Bayes' theorem
to learn from data.
Which treatment would you choose
if you needed a treatment?
Treatment one cured
100% of the patients.
Treatment two cured
95% in a trial.
And treatment three cured 90%.
All right.
There's some holdouts
for the 95% cure.
I'm not sure why.
What if I gave you
this information.
Treatment one cured three
out of three patients.
That's 100%.
Treatment two cured
19 of 20 patients.
That's 95%.
Or you have a standard
treatment which
has cured 90,000 out of
100,000 patients-- 90%.
PROFESSOR 2: So suppose
in this at MIT mug,
I have dice of two types--
four sided and 20 sided.
I'm going to randomly pull
out a die and roll it.
All right, I got a one.
Which type of die do you
think I randomly chose?
OK that was actually
what I had in this cup.
Does this change at all
of your analysis of which
die you think I rolled
and got a one with?
So this is the
first four question.
All right.
I want you to practice making
the table Jerry showed you.
Make one for if it were 13.
Make one if I rolled
a five instead.
Or do the same question
if I had rolled a nine.
MALE VOICE 1: He knew
it was a 20 sided die.
PROFESSOR 2: Your
beliefs have changed
based on that about the
probability that you
have each of the five dice.
So if you take that and
you use that as your prior
here, then the likelihood,
multiply and sum,
that should give you--
FEMALE VOICE: I Like that.
PROFESSOR 1: Right?
So I've lectured for years.
I don't know that I've ever
heard of that many oohs
and ahs or a statement,
I like that, at the end.
Sometimes there's a student
who nods very enthusiastically.
OK.
So what I'm going to go through
here is just what we do.
I'm going to resist the urge
to talk a lot about why we like
doing it, because
that will come later.
And John will talk about that.
The structure is we need
three times 80 minutes.
So that's 240 minutes, which
matches the five times 50
minutes that a
traditional class meets.
Three lecture hours,
two recitation.
So it's not more
time, but at all times
we have two teachers this year
and three assistant teachers
in the room.
So there's five instructors
in the room at all times.
What we have them do.
Before class, they
do some reading.
To get them to do
the reading, there's
reading questions which
they get credit for.
These are all online,
it's hosted on MITx,
and they get immediate feedback.
They know whether they got
the question right or wrong.
It's possible to ask lots
and lots of different types
of questions, although we
restrict ourselves mostly
to multiple choice and fill
in a number type of question.
Jenny French, who's here, has
done the same thing for 1803,
and she's been more ambitious
with the types of questions.
They come to class and we do
a minimal amount of lecturing.
What gets left out of a
math class of our class,
as opposed to a traditional
class lecture class,
is we don't do examples.
We're going to have the
students work examples,
and it's much more better,
much more better, much better
for students to work one
example than for the teacher
to work two.
We feel this strongly.
You saw that.
You saw a little
bit of lecturing.
It was cut.
I maybe lectured a little more
in the video than you saw,
but very quickly,
we have them up
at the boards doing
group problems
as you saw in the video, while
the teachers and the assistance
are circulating and
talking to people
and helping them get past
stumbling part points
and assessing what they're
understanding and correcting
misconceptions.
Other components of
the class but you
didn't see as much we have a
whole class discussions have
them discuss things that they're
tables in groups we can operate
on many levels of interaction
between students and students,
and students and teachers.
We also use a little bit of
technology clicker questions,
where we'll ask a
multiple choice,
usually a kind of
concept question
to see if they've
understood one idea,
and it also allows us
to take attendance.
And the students
see it that way.
Once a week, on
Fridays, we actually
do a computer
based studio, where
they have their computers.
It's the one time we let
them take their computers out
and we do it in our--
typically we're not
introducing new material.
We're doing more advanced
work or simulations
that you can do on the computer.
And finally, we do have
traditional problem sets.
They have to turn in the problem
set on paper once a week,
and its graded in the usual way.
The piece that checker
is not traditional.
This is something we borrowed
from the physics people.
Safe is here, I think.
I think you guys pioneered this.
It allows the students
to check their answers
to their homework ahead of time,
which allows us to tell them
we care about how
you present it,
that your logic and your
thinking is correct,
it allows the students--
I can't resist saying
this one thing's on, I'm sorry.
It allows the students to
reflect on the piece sets
as they're doing it.
One of the things we know
is when we turned back
a piece set a week
later, it's gone cold,
they've barely looked at it to
see what they've done wrong.
Here they see immediately it's
wrong, and they can reflect.
OK.
I think now we have an
active part of this.
John is going to--
PROFESSOR 2: We believe
strongly in active learning,
so we got to do some
active learning.
But really what I want
to take you through
is how we might envision a
particular new concept being
introduced to the students.
What are the various components
and how do they fit together?
So Jerry mentioned that we
have this unit, the middle unit
of our course, on
Bayesian inference.
And the first day we do a number
of problems that involve dice.
In particular, at the
beginning of the term,
we actually give
students dice that we
expect them to keep with
them throughout the term,
and we use them
to generate data,
and to do probability
experiments,
but also just to make
something tangible.
And so, in particular
on this first day,
the students will have come in
having done reading, maybe we
had about 10 pages, they
read, they answer some reading
questions.
And this introduces them
to some new concepts,
but doesn't expect them
to have mastered it.
And then in the beginning of
that class that you saw filmed,
we had some discussions
surrounding these dice.
So what you see here
is I have five dice.
This four sided.
This is a six sided
regular old die.
Eight, 12, and 20.
So these are platonic dice.
And the question I have
for you is as follows.
So I actually have
smaller versions.
I'm going to take them
and put them in this cup.
All right.
I'll shake it around.
Allison, reach in and grab
whatever and don't look.
All right.
Hand it to me.
Thank you.
And then Lourdes can you come
up and you're verify our here.
All right.
So four dice are
still in this cup.
Lourdes is going tell--
PROFESSOR 1: John.
John.
PROFESSOR 2: No.
I'll do it in the cup.
So you're going to
say what I roll.
OK.
I'm going to drop it
in, shake it around.
All right.
Just say the number.
Do not say which die.
OK?
What number do you see?
AUDIENCE: Four.
PROFESSOR 2: A four.
So which die do
you think I chose?
Raise your hand if you think
it's the four sided die.
Let's say which is
the most likely.
Raise your hand if you
think it's a six sided.
OK.
Eight?
12?
20?
Raise your hand if you
think actually they're
all equally likely
at this point.
Great.
So this is an example of
an excellent opportunity
to have a whole class
discussion, because clearly you
don't all agree.
So in our class, since they
sit around these tables of nine
people, we might
have them say, OK,
well discuss at the level of
your table-- you're all facing
each other-- and see
if you can come to some
So let's try to
convince each other.
All right.
Well I'm not going to tell
you the answer just yet.
Let's do another roll.
Maybe that'll help.
AUDIENCE: Is that the same die?
PROFESSOR 2: It's the same die.
I didn't, You saw.
It's not magic.
All right.
What I just roll?
AUDIENCE: A five.
PROFESSOR 2: A five.
Ooh.
OK.
So now raise your hand,
is it the four sided die?
Very good.
Six sided die?
OK.
Eight?
12?
20?
Are they all equally likely.
Raise your hand
if you still think
they're all equally likely.
That's interesting, right?
So there's been
some progress here.
Maybe discuss with
your neighbors now.
I'll give you 10 seconds.
PROFESSOR 1: All right.
This is great.
Usually it takes us
about a week and a half
before we get people to discuss
this animatedly while we
do things.
They have to learn to trust us.
That some discussions
I might call on people
to give explanations, but
in the interest of time,
let me just put a
few more time so I
got a six now I got a three now
I got up to now I got a one now
I got up six OK.
Raise your hand if you
think it a six sided die?
Wonderful.
All right.
PROFESSOR 2: So you
never know in science
whether you're right.
This is statistics.
I'm not statistics.
I'm not going to tell you.
Sorry.
No, that's the difference
between probabilities
and statistics.
You never know.
All right, so Great.
We've gotten the
students to appreciate
there's some interesting
question here,
maybe some intuition,
They've discussed it.
Next, what you saw
on the video was
the students' at the
board's, working on problems,
so they're actually doing
computations meant to take them
to the next level, whether
they're not just beginning
to appreciate that something's
going on, but to actually
rigorously mathematically
do some computations.
And they've seen examples
of this computation
in their reading.
And we're all going
around the room,
and we're helping,
interacting with the groups.
And after they do this,
they come back together, we
might discuss a
solution, maybe they're
be some clicker
questions involved,
and they'll still have
on Friday the studio.
In the, studio they might use r.
Perhaps we've
written a script that
simulates this rolling of a
die, and updates the prior
to the posterior
about which diet i is,
and then they'll experiment
with different situations
with a simulation, to
changing, some component of it.
We don't expect them
to be experts in r,
but we expect them to
be able to understand
code we've written and
modified in some way
to build their
conceptual understanding.
And then they'll
have a problem set.
The problem set will
ask them some questions
that build further.
And there will be
exams, and so on.
So that's the sort of
trajectory of seeing a topic
sort of building up your
level of understanding.
So now I'm going to
say a little bit now
about the whys a jury told
you of what we do here
level of little
bit about why we do
and what we've learned from
the experience of doing it,
and what we like.
So in terms of active learning
versus traditional lecture .
The first thing to note is
that just the physical act
of standing up, serves
many very useful purposes.
The first is that in a
given 80 minute session,
students might be up on their
feet, two or three times
for 10 to 15 minutes.
And when they're up,
they're not on the phone,
they're not on the computer,
and they're not asleep.
So those are all good things.
But even more, just
the act of standing,
it sort of in some ways
activates your focus.
You're at the board,
there aren't distractions,
you're with your group members,
and you have a task at hand.
And so just the physical
act of standing we find
is a way to raise the
energy in the room.
Now I'll not make all you
stand while we talk about this,
but I think you would agree
that standing wakes you up.
The physical space.
This is TEAL room
is kind of amazing,
but what's most
amazing about it is not
that it has all these
computers at the tables, which
at this stage isn't so useful,
because everyone has laptops.
It's not even really the
video cameras and projectors.
It's just the physical space is
such that students can rapidly
get out of the seats, find room
on the board, work on a problem
comfortably, come back,
sit at these tables,
their chairs swivel
without them getting up,
because they have little
rollers, it's carpeted,
so it's not too noisy.
There's just lots of things
about the physical space that
are really nice and
make the class possible.
So if we had a choice
between technology
versus just physical space,
we would choose the latter,
in a heartbeat.
And that means that in
classrooms where you might not
have white boards
everywhere, you
might want to think
about putting some up.
In Haiti we actually put
up paper on the walls
in order to do simulations
with professors there,
to get them to feel what
active learning was like,
at least the way
we were trying it.
Peer and teacher instruction.
So here there's a lot of
talk about peer instruction,
about how students can
help teach one another,
and that's really important.
And there's also
teacher instruction,
where the teacher's
interacting with the student,
and helping them move along
in their understanding.
And what we find in the
classroom is really happening
is a lot of both.
They're both important.
So the peer instruction happens
because they have discussions
at the table, or because
they're working together
at groups in the board.
In
Particular, at the
board, you might
have one student
who's very strong,
a couple others who aren't as
strong on a particular problem
on a particular problem,
and us going around
can very much encourage
the students who
seems to be taking the lead
to make sure the other group
members understand, or to try
to vary who's taking that lead.
But you see a lot of
students explaining
to each other, the students
being able to look over
at the next group if
they're stuck, all of this
is a kind of peer instruction.
But there's also the
teacher instruction,
which is the fact that
Jerry and I, and then
a graduate student and two
undergrads are in the room
able to basically distribute
ourselves like zone defense,
and monitor a certain
number of groups,
and really keep tabs on the
progress they're making.
Because you're
going to have groups
that are faster and slower, and
you want to kind of bring them
to about the same
point at the same time,
so they can get the
most out of the time
when you come to the
that explanation.
So that sort of interaction
between the teachers
and the students is
also really huge,
because the students actually
feel like they get to know us
and we get to feel
like we know them.
The student self assessment,
that's referring to the idea
that there's a really rich
formative assessment happening
in the classroom, when the
students are asked especially
to get up and solve
problems at the board.
When you listen
to teacher lecture
at you, doing an example,
you may nod your head
and think you understand it.
But when you're at a board, or
when you're using a clicker,
you actually have
to do the problem.
You figure out really
quickly if you understand it,
because if you're
standing there,
and you have no idea
where to get started,
you don't understand it.
And you know.
But you want to create an
environment where that's OK,
because maybe your
group mates know.
Or maybe we know.
And they're comfortable
saying, hey John, Jerry, can
you help us get started.
Or even better,
we're on top of them
even before they
get to that point,
because we have a sense at this
point which groups are going
to have the most
trouble getting started.
And there are some groups where
once you get them started,
they fly.
And it's just a matter of
being there at the beginning.
There are other groups
which are the reverse.
So you get to learn that
through this rich interaction.
And that self-assessment
the students say really
helps them know if they know.
Right?
Teacher formative assessment.
I guess I just mentioned that.
That's us being able to see
where these groups are at.
So the advantage of them
standing up at the board
is that from a distance
you can scan the room
and see very quickly how far
each student or group has
gotten on these problems, which
student is holding the pen
and are explaining.
By the time this
period has ended
where they've been
working on these problems,
you've helped several groups get
past several stumbling points.
So now comes time to bring
the cost back together
and go through an
explanation of those
parts which are most
helpful, and you know,
because you actually
already helped them.
It's like you had an office
hour where everyone attended,
and now you get to
explain the answer, right?
And so that's been
really exciting for us.
So those are some of the active
learning benefits we found.
And then in terms
of technology, there
are I guess three ways
for using technology
to enhance the class.
The reading questions
as Jerry said,
these are, by and large,
a way to get students
to at least open the PDF
that has the reading.
The students at MIT are going
to play some game theory
and manage their time to
balance a lot of obligations.
You can't expect them
to say your course is
the most important
course, and of course I'm
going to do this before
I do anything else.
But at least if they
get to the stage
where they open that
document, because they
know they're going to get
graded, 5% of the grade
on answering these
reading questions,
you have a good
chance that they're
going to have some
first exposure.
And if you create an expectation
at the beginning of the term
that we're going to assume
that they've done the reading,
and not go over it as if
they didn't, then that also
helps to enforce and get
students to actually do it.
So they are actually
graded on these questions
in terms of whether
they're right or wrong,
and they're not meant to be
particularly hard questions.
They're more like
questions that are exactly
parallel to an example,
so at least they
have to look through the
example, change the numbers,
plug-in an answer.
Clickers and attendance.
When you do an active
learning course,
it's even more important
that students come to class.
You can't watch an active
learning course on video
like you can watch a lecture.
And so in some sense, it's
a way to bring value back
to campus in the
face of [INAUDIBLE].
Well one way to force attendance
is to actually take attendance.
But we can do that
implicitly with the clickers.
So students know that
if they don't show up,
they're not clicking in
to certain questions,
they don't get any
points for that.
That's 5% of their grade.
Now we definitely have a
few students who are still
not going to show up at all,
because they ace every exam,
they learn it on
their own, great.
They'll get 95%, they'll
get an A in the course.
Right?
And that's OK.
It's not necessarily everyone
has to learn the same way,
but it's really important
for those students who
aren't able to do
everything on their own
that they come to class.
And we get a pretty
good attendance rate.
And we think the clickers
help incentivize that.
The piece that checker,
Jerry mentioned,
is a tool to get
students to know ahead
of time whether or not they
got their answer correct, so
that they still have time
to reflect and ask a friend
or think about it some
more while they might still
get some credit.
So there's still incentive.
As opposed to a
couple weeks later,
when the problems
that comes back,
they have three
other problem sets,
they have an exam,
it's not in RAM,
might as well not give
it back to them at all.
I can tell you how big the
stack of problem sets I have.
I mean, every day of every
week I bring them to the class.
I'm like, please, unburden me.
Take back these problem sets.
Most students don't
even want them back.
It just tells you
how little they're
benefiting from the grading
of the problem sets.
And I think this tool
in particular, transfers
very broadly very easily.
It doesn't have to be a math
class or a physics course.
It just has to be a course
where there's some way
to do some assessment,
or some way
to evaluate if a student
has made progress.
It might be there's a
formula and you just
plug-in some number and
that's how you know.
Granted they don't learn
what the answer is.
They just get told that 3.58
is not the right answer.
It's not very efficient for
them to then try 3.59, 3.57, you
know, it won't help them.
So they use it in a way that's
very satisfying if you're
taking a MOOC, which is you
get those green checks when
your answer's correct.
It feels great.
And so they know, great,
I figure these out.
I got green checks.
I'm turning this in.
It's going to be correct.
But they still get
graded on their logic
and on their writing.
That's the only part
of the problem set
that actually counts
toward the grade.
So I think those
are those points.
PROFESSOR 1: Right.
I can add that since it's
on MITx, we have analytics.
They use the piece
set checker for a lot.
Most students are using it.
I'd say well over 2/3.
And they go through,
you can see how many
attempts they're making
for the various questions.
Next slide.
Is it me?
PROFESSOR 2: I think
it's both of us.
PROFESSOR 1: Ah yeah.
So we'll give our
own takes on this.
So when you talk
about active learning,
there's some common questions.
So how much work was all this?
The answer was an unbelievably
large amount of work for us.
But part of that was
we changed everything.
So it's hard to
say what it would
be had we taught this
as a lecture course
for three or four years, had
we changed our curriculum
and added the Bayesian
unit before converting it
into an active learning
class, had we not
been so ambitious in
using the MITx platform,
all of those things would
have lessened the work.
But I think you could say
it's still a lot of work
to convert from a lecture
to a active learning format.
For one thing,
there's no faking what
you're going to do in an
active learning format.
We have slides, we
have to have questions,
well thought out
questions ahead of time.
You can't pull examples kind
of out of your hat the way
I would never do, but I've
heard that some people do
when they lecture.
How much are you able to cover?
This is also a typical question.
How can you cover as much?
The answers we find we can
cover at least as much.
I'll say a little
more about that.
You're cutting out examples,
you spend a lot of time
in a math class working
through examples.
The students are
doing the examples
so they're learning
the material better
than you're doing the examples.
And that time is from your doing
the examples is safe for them
to work.
In terms of 1805, it's a
little hard to measure.
We know we've added three
weeks worth of material
to the class we inherited.
It's possible that the class we
inherited was under ambitious.
And we could've added
that in a lecture class.
We know we cover the first
unit, the probability unit in--
PROFESSOR 2: I think five
weeks instead of seven.
PROFESSOR 1: FIve
And they do just as well
on comparable exams.
So I think I feel
safe in saying that we
cover at least as much material.
You spend more time
in the classroom
because as the teachers, we're
in there for all 240 minutes.
None of it is pawned off
on recitation leaders.
It might be interesting
to know whether that's
really necessary
for all the teachers
to be there all the time.
Do you have anything
to add to that, John?
PROFESSOR 2: I think for us, one
thing that added a lot of work
was that when we decided
to change the curriculum,
we realized there was no
textbook that taught what we
wanted to teach, so we
had wrote the textbook.
And that takes a lot of time.
PROFESSOR 1: Yeah, I
said that was in November
for a class that was starting in
January that we finally decided
we had to throw
away the textbook.
PROFESSOR 2: Right.
So in the end, we
wrote these materials,
but I can say that
the students really
appreciated that the
reading they were doing
was very targeted.
It told them the
objectives, exactly what
we expected of them, what kinds
of problems, at what level,
and so it turned out to
have other benefits we
didn't foresee going in.
And then in terms of how
much we're able to cover,
like Jerry said, we gave
exactly the same first midterm
three years in a row.
We're not going to give
it a fourth year in a row,
so don't--
PROFESSOR 1: No.
We added one question.
PROFESSOR 2: Plus one question.
So because we gave
exam at seven weeks,
the first time we
taught it, that
was just the probability unit.
The second and third time
we taught it-- so third time
is right now-- that was
the probability unit
plus like a week or
two of more stuff.
Right?
So it had one more question.
Like six instead
of five questions.
And if you remove the
one more question,
they actually did as
well or slightly better
compared to the first unit.
If you include it, they did
it pretty much the same.
But you have the same amount
of time to take the exam,
so it's a pretty concrete
measure that they did better.
Now we don't know that
that's because in part we
actually understood a
little more statistics
and could explain better
the second time around.
PROFESSOR 1: No, this
is just probability.
We understood probability.
PROFESSOR 2: We did
understand probability.
OK.
That was good.
PROFESSOR 1: We should
say, so neither of us
are statisticians.
Going in we've learned
a lot of statistics,
and particularly
how to teach it.
I don't think at a
mathematical level
the statistics we're
doing is terribly hard,
but we all believe
I think as teachers
that the more
expertise you have.
So Sansa, who I
mentioned earlier,
does know a lot of statistics
and has been consulting with us
and been a tremendous asset in
getting us up to speed on this.
AUDIENCE: Question.
How did you know that
the students didn't
cheat, for example,
and have access
to the previous year's exams?
PROFESSOR 1: You ask
a really good question
but I think you can infer that
from reading their papers.
If you read the papers,
students are not
getting everything right.
PROFESSOR 2: By the
way, we did change
the wording, the
topic, the numbers.
I mean we didn't leave it so you
could just put the same answer.
And doing it a
third year was kind
of stretching the limits of
what you're exactly asking.
PROFESSOR 1: We
won't do it again.
I will say this, and I
often get into a discussion
about cheating, which is I
could give-- I know from lecture
classes and maybe Arthur
will verify this who's
sitting there, Arthur Maddock,
whose done a lot of lecturing--
I've seen when I've teach
recitation that I can tell
my students, the teacher has
given you practice questions.
Three of them will
be on the exam.
Two of the questions on the
exam will be just small changes
of this, and I still know that
many students won't find time
to do the practice exam.
I think it's kind of a myth.
If they found my exam in
the copier-- well actually
most of them would return it to
me-- but someone might cheat.
But the effort of going to
try to do something like this
without being certain that
you're going to be getting
something that's going
to be on the exam,
it just doesn't
happen that often.
So I think now if it
comes out that we'd
give the same exam
year in and year out,
people will look at it.
So we won't do that again.
Other observations.
This is kind of the
psychological observations.
Active learning is a lot
more fun for the students.
You could see even in that
video when they stand up,
there's a lot of energy
in the classroom.
You could hear the buzz.
People are not sleeping.
Co-teaching, if you can
do it, is tremendous fun.
I can't get away with anything
with John standing there.
I'm a little more
generous to him.
I let him make mistakes.
Students like getting
to know their teachers.
This is a really
important value at MIT.
A number of students
graduate from MIT
without knowing enough
teachers well enough
to get three letters
of recommendation.
Here, we're walking
around, were meeting them,
both of us like students,
and like talking to students.
And they appreciate it,
they did get to know us,
we have to write a lot more
letters of recommendation
than we ever did before.
There's a downside
to everything.
The students like
the targeted reading.
In fact, Glenda Stump, who is
with the teaching and learning
laboratory here and has
done surveys of our students
and interviews with our
students, the report-- and this
was interesting to us-- they
like the reading more than they
like watching videos.
Videos take longer.
The targeted reading is
just what they need to know.
We're telling them, this is
what we expect you to learn,
and it doesn't take as
much time as a video.
And finally, students really
love the piece set checker.
It gives them a very
comfortable feeling.
So finally, looking
forward, Glenda
is continuing to study
what we're doing.
At some point there
will be a paper report
that comes out of this.
The course will be on
OpenCourseWare and the OCW
educator, where we'll give--
it's being videotaped here,
so this talk might show up
on OpenCourseWare educator,
to tell other teachers
about what we're doing,
as well as present
the course materials.
And finally, and
this is important,
we've overstaffed the
class in the sense
of what the budgets
will really allow.
We've had a Davis foundation
grant that helps with it.
The math department
has supported it.
We have to move to a more
traditional staffing.
So actually next year, I'll
teach the class by myself,
without John's help.
We'll see what we do.
I'll have to learn how
do these sort of demos,
because we leave that to John.
And with just the undergraduates
and maybe a graduate student
in the class.
This year John
didn't say it, but we
have actually another
instructor who's
a statistician in
the class with us--
Peter Kempthorne at all times.
And then equally important
for a project like this
is making a transition
to the next teacher.
We're to have to
convince someone else
that they want to teach like
this, and they want to do it.
Part of our strategy will
be, after three years,
to have such a compelling
set of materials
that it's so easy
for them to use,
that it won't feel
like as much work.
So that's what we're looking
forward to in the future.
Finally, come visit.
We have had visitors.
We like it when
people come to visit.
If you send us a
note, we'll tell you
what's a good day to visit.
If not, you can take it
chances and just show up.
We're in the basement
of the Stata Center
in the TEAL room, which
we should have mentioned.
This is in part an outgrowth
of the physics TEAL project.
PROFESSOR 2: It's a huge room.
There's plenty of space.
So you don't have to
worry it'll be full.
PROFESSOR 1: You saw in
the video it's a big room.
Stata Tuesday, Thursday
and Friday at 1:00 to 2:30.
Come for all or part of it.
PROFESSOR 2: And I should say
that Tuesday and Thursday are
really the days our sort
of standard clip days.
And then Fridays are when
we do that studio with r,
and they have the computers.
So it's a bit different.
And of course some
weeks they have exams.
So you might not want
to come on an exam day.
That won't be as interesting.
So you might just let us know
when you're going to show up.
AUDIENCE: What's the
size of your [INAUDIBLE]?
PROFESSOR 1: We have
about 60 students.
Right now the room
could comfortably hold,
I think 90 people.
So the class actually
had about 31,
32 students two years
ago when we took it over
as a lecture course.
Last year that bumped
up to the low 40s.
The first time
theories are flipped,
and now we have 60, or
maybe 58 the second time
through, so we're hoping
that we can keep that going.
AUDIENCE: Do you find that it's
more work to teach the class--
PROFESSOR 1: No.
I find it less work once
you're in the class.
If you have the slides
prepared and you
spend a lot of time
walking around just
schmoozing with students.
And working.
No, it's not.
It's easier, it's
more energizing,
I'm never tired when
we're done, I never
feel that I've just
droned on for 40 minutes
and not modulated
my voice at all.
So it's not more work to teach.
It's more work to
prepare, I should say.
You have to be fully prepared.
There's no thinking
about, yeah what
is this topic on the
way to the lecture,
and giving the
example, and being
confident that you'll be able
to work it out the next line
before you get there.
AUDIENCE: You might have heard
but we don't have the body
to staff like this, knowing
how much money we had.
So I guess I'm wondering, how
does the need for staffing
scale with enrollment, if
you 90 students show up?
PROFESSOR 1: The
physics department
has been doing this
for a lot of years.
They have one
instructor in the room
and typically a lot
of graduate students
who would be teaching
a recitation otherwise.
So you can staff it in that
way with one instructor
and graduate students.
Undergraduates,
good undergraduates,
are also very good.
It's a little harder
to find students
who are free Tuesday,
Thursday and Friday.
I think maybe next year, because
Friday is just the studio,
and there's less of a need,
they do less on Friday.
If I get students just
on Tuesday and Thursday,
we'll do it.
But there's a lot of
very good undergraduates
who are quite helpful.
AUDIENCE: I think granted a lot
of the grading is automatic.
Is that the only
thing [INAUDIBLE]?
PROFESSOR 1: No.
The good--
PROFESSOR 2: No.
It's not automatic at all.
PROFESSOR 1: The piece sets
are graded by Graders on Paper.
PROFESSOR 2: Undergraduates.
PROFESSOR 1:
Undergraduate graders.
That's the same as if we
taught it as a lecture.
You have to hire them.
It's easier to find
graders because they
don't commit to being
in a certain place
at a certain time.
AUDIENCE: I asked
you this at lunch.
Did you get feedback
from students
that help you refine it or make
you think about the things that
maybe weren't so good and things
that were especially good?
PROFESSOR 1: Yes.
So the first year we did
the studio in MATLAB,
and it's not MATLAB's fault.
PROFESSOR 2: It wasn't MA fault.
PROFESSOR 1: It's
not MATLAB's fault.
It was our fault.
It was really tedious.
We did a lot of tutorials
on using the software,
and so was click
here, click there.
You have students at
very different levels.
MIT students are very good.
If you show them a
program, a script--
you don't write complicated
scripts with a lot of logic.
It's typically just
a series of commands
that you can get out
of this-- they're
able to see what's
going on and use it.
So it's based on
feedback from them.
Part of it is just
being in the room
and realizing how dull it was.
But also from
talking to students.
We changed that.
What else?
We did get feedback
on others but I'm
forgetting what they say.
PROFESSOR 2: But we
got feedback fact
that it's good to have the
full week's materials posted
before the week
starts, which was very
challenging the first year,
because we were often writing
it like at that exact moment.
This year we've corrected that.
As far as using the software, I
think exactly what Jerry said,
plus I'll add that
we had to think,
we thought more of
what our goals were
with them interacting
with the software.
And really it was
less about making
them experts in
using MATLAB or R,
and more about leveraging
the software as a way
to increase their
understanding of the material.
And from that
point of view, it's
not quite as necessary
to have them build up
complicated things from
scratch, but rather
to be able to understand
something we've written
and well enough that they
can change components, play
with it, visualize things,
and so we've really
moved in that direction.
And also another piece
of feedback we got
was that students really
appreciate real world
applications, especially
lot of them are pre-med,
they want to see
medical research papers,
they want to see data
that speaks to them.
And so Peter
Kempthorne for example,
has a background in
the financial world,
so he's helped us create
some studios centered
around stock prices
moving around.
The one we created last week was
a studio where basically they
used a two dimensional
Bayesian updating
to simulate looking
for Malaysia flight 370
under the Indian Ocean
by putting a sensor grid.
PROFESSOR 1: And it
was found the next day.
Or they got that ping.
PROFESSOR 2: That's right.
Right?
They're not going to know how
to make this sort of heat map
representation or a contour
plot representation,
the posterior of updating
based on what sensors detected,
and so on, but that's OK.
We can instead give
them the framework,
they can play with it.
We can say, well, what
happens if instead
of the black box being
right in the middle
of this grid of
sensors, it's up here.
And then they realize
after playing with it,
oh, actually it takes
longer to converge
and at first the probability
sort of spread out this way,
and why is that,
oh, because it's
about the same
distance left to right.
Those things were coming
naturally to them.
Didn't mean they
had to understand
how to do this
complicated syntax,
but it was a benefit of getting
these visuals right away
to play around.
AUDIENCE: And relevant to
what was of interest to them
because their field
or something--
PROFESSOR 2: Well in this case,
it was relevant to the New York
Times report the
night before, which
said that they were deploying
sensors behind ships.
So we talked about
how would you modify
this to make it
more realistic based
on what they're actually
doing, which isn't so hard.
And they got the
idea of hopefully
that this stuff is useful.
PROFESSOR 1: So
these are details.
I think part of the point is
we're always getting feedback
from the students,
because that's
part of what happens in
a classroom, the kind
of formative assessment
John mentioned.
One of the things we've
done, and it differs
from what TEAL
does, is a question
is, how long do you let
them work on a problem?
And through their feedback,
through talking to them,
and through observation, we've
kind of converged on how long
you go with a problem.
And I think one of the
differences with TEAL
is we give them a longer
time to solve problems
than they do in
TEAL, and they do
express an
appreciation for that.
How did you learn
to work effectively
in the TEAL classroom?
Did you observe others?
Did you have special training?
PROFESSOR 1: No.
We went to Peter
[? Damascan's ?] class,
we talked with Peter, the
day before our first class,
we went into the room
and we rehearsed it down
to the minute.
And then we just sort of
tried it over and over again.
We were lucky the
first day, partly
I think because of the
rehearsal was so successful.
Haynes you probably
remember how high
we were flying after that day.
And so--
PROFESSOR 2: The
level of preparation,
quickly deteriorated after.
PROFESSOR 1: No, no, no.
We don't do it
down to the minute.
We're more confident in
the 10 minute intervals,
but we're well prepared.
PROFESSOR 2: The room is, I
mean there's a little control
panel you just need to learn
how to make the screens go up
and down, or make a video
camera go on or off.
Make the lights go up or down.
It's not that
that's challenging,
but it definitely took
a lot of trial and error
to optimize what's the best
way to use those technologies,
and that was experimentation
we got better as we went.
PROFESSOR 1: I don't think
the technology was as much.
But things like how long
do you do a problem.
In the first year, I'd
be off in the corridor
talking with students and
John would come and say,
you know, it's been a long time.
It's time to stop.
And I think maybe it happened
in reverse on occasion.
PROFESSOR 2: It's a
really common problem
with active learning is
that you do have groups
that will go at
different speeds.
One advantage with
having enough staffing
is that you can try to
target those groups,
get people to about
the same point.
There are always going
to be winners and losers
in any approach you take
the teaching a class.
We're not claiming
that what we're doing
is better for everyone.
But just this feedback you get
as you're doing it dynamically
in the hour, it really helps.
It really helps you
know how to reach them.
AUDIENCE: Did you have
a schedule of we're
going to do this for 10 minutes,
we're going to do this for 15.
Did you have [INAUDIBLE]?
PROFESSOR 1: We have it
broken down by slides.
And so the slides do it.
PROFESSOR 2: We have a
slide presentation that
is prepared ahead, so it
does give you an order.
PROFESSOR 1: And
at this point, you
learn when you prepare lectures.
At this point we know that
16 slides we can get through,
20 slides we're not
going to get through.
PROFESSOR 2: We
should also say that--
PROFESSOR 1: We fall still
into the mistake of thinking,
oh, we could do it.
We could do it.
But you never do.
PROFESSOR 2: One
thing we also do
that students I think appreciate
is that you're still not going
to get every student to
understand the problem they
just did necessarily in the
confines of the class time.
And there might be times
where it doesn't make sense
to go through every
detail of a problem,
because it wouldn't
be that efficient,
because most students
basically got it.
And so the version of the
slides that we post right before
and use in the class is
different from the updated
version we post
after class, which
includes complete careful
solutions to every problem
that we did in
class, so students
know that that's there for them.
They might feel like
they're missing out.
They want to see an expert
solve the problem the right way.
Why should they have to come
up with that way completely
themselves.
And so we capture some of
that by putting that in there.
PROFESSOR 1: But you
should say, we usually
do solve it for them afterwards.
Most problems we give them
the expert nice succinct view.
And I think that's an
important part of this.
Students want to
feel that they're
getting some of your expertise.
AUDIENCE: You mentioned students
prepare the targeted questions
reading to online
lectures, I was
wondering what
students felt was so
good about the targeted reading
or what it was that was so bad
the online lectures.
PROFESSOR 1: I
don't think they'd
say the online lectures are bad.
Online lectures take longer
to watch if you try to MOOC.
And how many people in
this room have tried.
The videos are long.
I mean you always are looking
to try to speed it up, find
the two times speed
up, et cetera.
They can take a long time.
The target, the fact that
the reading is target,
the fact that we wrote it, and
it covers what we expect them
to learn, is, I think,
the main thing they like.
There's clear signals in there,
we think this is important.
Not we said read
chapter five and you
have to figure out by
listening to us which
parts of chapter
five are important.
PROFESSOR 2: And
I mean those are
skills that as you go higher
up in your education at MIT,
you might be able to
do more for yourself,
and you should learn the skills.
But I think the
level of this course,
I mean many of these
students, they're
strong mathematically by
national standards of course,
but maybe within MIT if
they're life science majors,
they're not as confident
as some of the math majors
in physics majors.
It helps them to have
a little more guidance
in what the expectations are.
What do you do for
small groups where
there's a group
that's gotten done,
and everyone else
is still working?
Do you have extra stuff
for their enrichment?
PROFESSOR 1: You can walk around
and try to challenge them.
Most groups is rare
that there's people
who have understood,
particularly
say the first time we
work through an idea
have understood it completely.
So there's always questions.
You could say, have
you thought about this,
or what if you did that?
AUDIENCE: How do
you form the groups
and do you change them during
the course of the semester?
PROFESSOR 1: No.
We let them form themselves.
I think there's a debate in
the education community--
maybe Jenny can speak to this--
about whether it's better
to form the groups,
for you to form them
by some sort of heterogeneous
ability, or to let them form.
We feel that, first
of all, we don't
know their ability coming in.
Second, people like autonomy.
And so allowing them to form
groups makes them comfortable.
There are students who
are resistant to this idea
of active learning coming in.
We win them over
quickly, and part of it
is the more generous
say in that sense.
AUDIENCE: What do you
if you see in one group
there's a dominant
member or there
are people who are sitting back?
PROFESSOR 1: You know it
doesn't happen that much.
Groups of three, they
tend to work together.
These are largely juniors
and seniors at MIT.
A few sophomores.
They have become better
at being students
and making sure they're
getting what they want.
There are some
groups where you come
and you try to draw people in.
It tends to be the groups
that are overall weaker,
where you see
people hanging back.
But those are exactly the
groups where you go to first,
and you spend more
time with them.
AUDIENCE: You mentioned the
flip component of the course.
So can you give a
little bit more idea
about your expectations
time-wise and material-wise
and you coordinate it?
I guess that they have these
readings, maybe 10 pages,
for every class?
Or week?
PROFESSOR 1: Twice a week.
Tuesday and Thursday.
So prior to Tuesday
and Thursday,
they need to do
reading, about 10 pages.
It's a very fast 10 pages.
We use a lot of white space.
AUDIENCE: What are
the problem sets?
Is there one problem
set per week?
And also one more
follow-up question
on that, what's the
turn-around for the assessment
and feedback for
those piece sets
so that they could hopefully
learn for the next one?
PROFESSOR 1: They have
one piece set per week,
except in weeks where we
have an exam and vacations.
So usually, let's say, one per
week, with some variations.
PROFESSOR 2: So the piece sets,
the way we structure it, right?
They're learning say
some new material
Tuesday, Thursday,
studio on Friday.
And the piece set
we have due Monday.
And the idea is that by
turning it on Monday,
they still then Monday night
can prepare for Tuesday's class.
We try to get the
graders to turn back
the piece set by the end
of the week, by Friday.
I'm not convinced that
getting that problem set back
is actually helping that
many students in the end.
Like I said, half the students
don't even pick them up.
PROFESSOR 1: But it is nice
for the students that want it.
So it's been good.
The graders get
it back by Friday.
PROFESSOR 2: Oh yeah, the
graders, they've done that.
AUDIENCE: How many
questions do you
expect them to work
through that piece set?
PROFESSOR 1: OK.
So the piece set is just
the challenging part
of a problem set we would ask
in a regular lecture class.
They've done more of
the drill problems
in class, and somewhat
on the reading questions.
So five or six
questions, which is
about what we would have on
what we call the part two
part of a regular
lecture class what they
would see in 1801
or 1802 or 1803.
AUDIENCE: About the grading
of the problem sets.
One thing that a lot of
education research shows
is that if there's a delay
between the act of doing
the problem and
the feedback, they
don't pay any attention,
which is what you're saying.
What if you force them to
actually think about it
again by grading the
problem set themselves.
So you could say, everyone
upload their problem
set, and then you get
somebody else's problem set,
and you have to then grade
it with your solution.
PROFESSOR 1: I think
it's a great idea.
One of my questions about
it would be two folds.
The students are not
going to like it,
especially when you
start them doing it.
And is it the best
use of their time?
I don't know what the
research shows on that.
AUDIENCE: We're writing
[INAUDIBLE] the solution set is
probably worth their
time reading it.
Otherwise--
PROFESSOR 1: Oh I see.
If they have to grade they
have to read our solutions.
AUDIENCE: And really
understand them,
and also learn what counts as a
good argument and what doesn't.
[INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR 1: I
can tell you this.
[? Analea ?] [? Bronte ?], who
I teach with in the experimental
study group, who
teaches physics there,
she did try to do
this at some point,
and she did learn that students
become good at grading it.
You don't have to
worry about that.
Over time with your
feedback, they learn to grade
pretty close to what
you would grade.
The questions.
She would give them a rubric
but she no longer does it.
There's a lot of
resistance to it.
AUDIENCE: By the students.
PROFESSOR 1: By the students.
PROFESSOR 2: You would hope
that a little bit of that
occurs before exams.
But I'm not sure.
AUDIENCE: Are you
collecting data more
than you would in
a regular class?
[INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR 2: Do you
mean like the sort
of data coming in
from the students.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR 1: Here's
the data that we have.
There's something called the
statistics concept inventory,
and we had them last
year do a pre-test.
And we have them do a post-test,
but we got to it too late,
so we couldn't
assign it to them.
It was in the last
week of class where
you can't assign things at MIT.
So we didn't get a lot
of compliance here.
This year they did the
pre-test, and the post-test
will be an assignment
for them to do.
So we'll be able to
measure how well they
improve on the
concept inventory.
It's not a perfect
match for what we do.
It has no Bayesian
component to it.
But we'll get a measure there.
The other is what
Glenda has done
with surveys and interviews.
And finally there are
analytics on MITx,
so we can see how long they've
spent at least with the PDFs
open, how many tries they
took at various questions.
We haven't tried to analyze
that data yet, but we could.
MODERATOR: OK.
I think so we won't have people
starting to get up and leave.
Thank you guys.
I think it strikes me is
it's one of those really
in the trenches talks.
We were actually
doing it and you
can hear the width from
the questions this time.
We sort of moved from a sort
of theoretical construct
and you could do
it this way where
it's actually happening around.
A lot of people are
thinking about it
and just thank you so much.