The following
content is provided
under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue
to offer high quality
educational resources for free.
To make a donation or
view additional materials
from hundreds of MIT courses,
visit MIT OpenCourseWare
at ocw.mit.edu.
PROFESSOR: All right, I guess
we can get started here.
So welcome.
Today we're going to do
Bayesian updating, which
is to say we're going to
be using Bayes' Theorem
to learn from data.
We're going to
update our beliefs
about various hypotheses
based on the data.
For this week, we're going
to have known priors.
We're going to know our
belief about the data ahead
of time for certain.
We'll draw coins out of
drawers or pull things out
of hats, things like that.
Starting next week,
and we discussed
this a little last time,
we'll have unknown priors,
which is you'll have to
be making up those priors.
And we'll teach you
techniques for making it up.
So the first slide is just
XKCD's view of Bayes' Theorem.
Let's go on.
We want to start with a
clicker question here.
So the question is which
treatment would you
choose if you
needed a treatment?
Treatment 1 cured
100% of the patients.
Treatment 2 cured
95% in a trial.
And treatment 3 cured 90%.
So with this information
which would you choose?
AUDIENCE: With only
this information?
PROFESSOR: With only this.
If this is all I told you.
Which would you choose?
I recognizing that you might
not be too happy with just
this information, but if this
is their best information, what
would you choose?
All right, there's some
hold outs for the 95% cure.
I'm not sure why.
Really, that 95%
was just, you know,
they've cured one
person 19 out of 20.
They got them 19 out of 20
well, or however you say that.
Yeah.
All right, so there's
even a few more holdouts.
All right, what if I gave
you this information?
Treatment 1 cured 3
out of 3 patients.
That's 100%.
Treatment 2 cured
19 of 20 patients.
That's 95%.
Or, you have a
standard treatment
which has cured 90,000 out
of 100,000 patients, 90%,
in clinical practice.
Now which one would you choose?
PROFESSOR 2: It's
very interesting.
Yeah, it totally changed.
PROFESSOR: What's that?
PROFESSOR 2: It totally shifted.
PROFESSOR: It totally
shifted, really?
PROFESSOR 2: We have a bunch
of very conservative people.
PROFESSOR: Right.
So the majority would
choose the third choice,
90 out of 100,000.
I think-- well someone tell
me, what's the intuition there?
AUDIENCE: Because
it's been more tested.
PROFESSOR: It's
been more tested.
3 out of 3 is 100%, but do
you really believe 100%?
Not yet.
Maybe it'll prove out in time.
19 out of 20 is a little
more, but for most people,
for 79% of you,
that's not enough.
The 90 out of 100,000
seems like good odds,
and it's well tested.
19 out of 20, if the next person
tested doesn't get better,
now you back to 90%.
So that doesn't seem
like quite enough.
What if were 95 out
of 100 patients.
We'll let you click in there.
Change number 2 to 95
out of 100 and let's
see what people would do.
Oh, you're very
obliging, 95 out of 100--
PROFESSOR 2: Now
it's about 50-50.
PROFESSOR: About 50-50.
PROFESSOR 2: Between 2 and 3.
PROFESSOR:
Realistically, of course,
what would you want to do?
You'd want to do a
little more research
and find out what these trials
were, how good experiments you
thought they were, what
people are thinking about it.
But with just this data, that's
what people would choose.
And would people would
choose differently.
OK.
PROFESSOR 2: Let's see.
So now I'm going to give you
a toy problem that actually
mirrors the same kind of effect
we saw on the last slide.
So, suppose in this MIT mug,
I have dice of two types,
4-sided and 20-sided.
All right?
So I'm going to
reach into the mug.
I'm not going to look.
Much.
I'm going to randomly
pull out a die.
I'm going to roll it.
All right, I got a 1.
OK.
I got a 1.
Now, just based on this
information, which type of die
do you think I randomly chose?
The 4-sided.
Someone want to give
an explanation of why
they think the 4-sided
is more likely?
AUDIENCE: It's
greater probability.
PROFESSOR 2: It's
What's the probability of
getting a 1 on the 4-sided die?
And what about a 20-sided sided?
OK.
So we see that it would
be more likely to roll a 1
with a 4-sided die than
with a 20-sided die.
So, suppose I tell you that
I really in this cup only
have one die of each type.
So does that change
your analysis
of which die is most likely?
Don't hit forward yet.
PROFESSOR: I would think of it.
My hands are staying.
PROFESSOR 2: Or do you want to
stick with the same reasoning?
All right.
Let me show you what's
actually in this cup.
PROFESSOR: Ouch.
PROFESSOR 2: Oh, you
can't see it yet.
Let's go with the
document camera.
OK, that was actually
what I had in this cup.
Now what?
So does this change at
all of your analysis
which die you think I
rolled and got a 1 with?
What type of die, rather?
AUDIENCE: Yes.
PROFESSOR 2: Yeah?
Now what do you
think is more likely?
4-sided or 20-sided?
AUDIENCE: How many
20-sided are there?
PROFESSOR 2: I think I
got 20 20-sided die there.
All right, so raise your hand
if you like a 4-sided die.
Raise your hand if you
like the 20-sided die.
Great.
So that reasoning that
you're doing intuitively
is something that we want
to formalize this week
and next week using
Bayes' Theorem
to do these calculations
in a systematic way,
to evaluate hypotheses
based on data.
And these numbers,
for example, how many
die I had of one
type versus another,
we can encode that information
in what's called a prior,
and we'll come to that today.
And you should've seen in
your reading this idea.
PROFESSOR: OK so I'm going
to work through an example
to start with.
We have 3 types of coins:
type A, B, and C. However
it happens, the probability
of getting heads with type A
is 0.5.
That's a fair coin.
The probability of getting
heads with type B is 0.6,
and of type C is 0.9.
And here's a box that
contains two of the fair coins
and one of each of the other.
So two of type A, one of
type B, and one of type C.
Suppose I pick one at
random and I get heads.
So this is like John picking a
die at random, and getting a 1.
I get heads.
Here's the question:
before I flipped it,
I have a prior belief
in the probability
that the coin was
of each type based
on the number in my drawer.
After flipping it,
my believe changes.
The probability will change
based on the data I get.
And so a question
you could ask: what
was learned by
flipping the coin?
What we want to teach you to
do to answer these questions,
we have a nice
way of summarizing
all of that once in a table.
So here the notation, we
have this nice scripty H--
that's no good.
H is our hypothesis.
That is, you're of
type A or B or C.
We're going to make a conjecture
on what we think the coin was.
Before we do anything,
we have a prior.
So what's the
probability of-- how
did I label this-- that
the coin was of type A?
Where all you know is I
pulled it out of the drawer.
So what's the probability
it's of type A.
PROFESSOR 2: Let me
go back and remind you
what the drawer looks like.
What is it?
PROFESSOR: 0.5.
0.5, or I'll write it like this.
2 out of 4, which is 0.5.
And what's the
probability-- I'll
shorten this-- for just
type B. Yeah, 1/4 or 0.25.
The probability that we're
of type C is 1/4 or 0.25.
This was one of our
simpler counting problems.
In the table, you can
see that's encoded
in the line in the
column marked prior.
Before we take any data,
this is what we'd say.
This is the sort
of odds we'd give
if we were going to bet on this.
But now we have some data.
So once we have data we
can get the likelihood.
The likelihood is
the probability
of seeing the data
given a hypothesis.
I won't write this out, I'll
just point at the slide.
John has a-- you were going
to make your mouse bigger.
PROFESSOR 2: I was.
PROFESSOR: OK.
So the likelihood column,
we use this term when
we are talking about
maximum likelihood,
is the probability of the
data given the hypothesis.
And this is typically easy,
or often easy, to figure out.
What's the probability
of seeing heads?
Our data was I flipped a heads
if my coin is a 0.5 probability
coin.
So the probability of seeing
heads given a type A coin
is what?
Somebody.
It's 0.5.
This is particularly
easy because that's
what we told you.
The probability of heads
with a type A coin is 0.5.
What about for B
and C. 0.6 and 0.9.
So there right here is the
likelihood column in the table.
Now, how do we
get the posterior?
Bayes' Theorem says
the probability of H
given D, which is what I want.
I want to know,
given this data, what
do I believe the coin to be?
What's its probability?
Is the probability of D given
H times the probability of H
all over the probability of D.
Well notice this
numerator right here.
That's just our likelihood
times our hypothesis,
our prior belief
in our hypothesis.
And so what do we get when
I multiply the prior column
by the likelihood column?
I get this column in red.
And I'll call that the
unnormalized posterior.
Why unnormalized because
it doesn't sum to 1.
How do I get it to sum to 1?
There I have to divide by
the probability of the data.
And how do I get the
probability of the data?
That's called the-- I
see someone mouthing it.
The Law of Total Probability.
And the Law of Total
Probability says
you multiply for each hypothesis
this value times this value
and add them up.
Which is in fact just the
sum of the red column.
So there I've written it 0.625.
And now how do I normalize?
I just divide by all my values
in my unnormalized column
by that normalizing
factor, 0.625,
and I get these, what
I call the posterior.
Let's say-- well now
let's analyze this.
So now what's your belief?
Which coin is the
most likely coin?
After seeing this data.
Still A. But what's
happened to the probability
from our prior probability?
It's dropped.
Which one has
gained probability.
AUDIENCE: C.
PROFESSOR: C. Does
that make sense?
If I flip a heads, which coin is
the most likely to flip heads?
C. So I've shifted it.
Suppose I flipped
heads three more times.
What would you see in the
probability as I kept updating?
PROFESSOR 2: Say it again.
AUDIENCE: The probability
of C gets bigger.
PROFESSOR 2: The
probability of C
would get bigger at the
expense of the probabilities
of the others.
If I flipped heads
9 times in a row,
I'd be very convinced
that I had a type C coin.
One last thing to
note about this table.
I put totals down here.
What does this total of 1
represent in the first column?
Emily.
AUDIENCE: The
total probabilities
of anything, so the total space.
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
When I sum up the
total probabilities,
they sum up to 1.
Same with this last.
That's a probability.
This I could sum, because
they were probabilities.
Why didn't I sum this column?
Those are the
likelihoods, and what's
changing as I move
down this column?
What's changing is H. That's
not a probability function.
It doesn't sum to 1.
There's no reason that the
likelihoods have to sum to 1,
and here you can see they
clearly don't sum to 1.
So I don't sum that.
That's an important, maybe
slightly subtle point,
that the likelihood function
is not a probability function.
OK, any questions here?
PROFESSOR 2: All right.
So, let's go back to
this document camera.
I got my trusty platonic solids.
So, we're going to go through a
series of board questions now,
three board questions which are
going to allow you to practice
making these tables and getting
a sense for how to do Bayesian
Updating, how to iterate
it, just how it works.
And our toy problem
is going to be
involving these 5 platonic dice.
You all have them, but let's
not break them out today,
because it would be very noisy
with the cameras I think.
We'll use our 4-sided--
here, I got big ones.
We've got our 4-sided,
8-sided, 6-sided.
No 6-sided.
No, I don't have a 6-sided.
I have the wrong dice.
Hold on.
We got 20, we got
4, we got 12, we
got 8, ah-- 10, what
are you doing there?
That's not platonic.
OK, and 6.
So now I'm actually
going to take these.
You can watch this.
All right, this is empty cup.
OK, they're in there right?
OK.
How do we do this?
How do we convince them?
PROFESSOR: Should we
choose one at random?
PROFESSOR 2: Yeah.
All right, choose it.
Don't let anyone see.
Hand it me.
OK.
So I have this die.
Don't look at the others.
I'm going to start
rolling it, all right?
In this secret bin.
Jerry, you can ver-- we
can have a student come
verify that I'm
not making this up.
You ready?
OK, here we go.
OK, what did I get?
8.
All right.
So, which die is it so far?
What do you think?
Could it be 4, the 4-sided die?
6-sided?
8?
12?
20?
What's most likely?
All right.
Come take a look at another one.
Ready?
Ah, got a 1.
AUDIENCE: It's the same die?
PROFESSOR 2: It's the same
die, it's the same die.
All right, so now what?
How does this
change, anyone want
to tell me how would
this now change
from before what
you believe to be?
Does it change what you
believe at all, in any way?
You still think
it's the 8-sided.
Does it make the 8-sided less
like, more likely relative
to the others?
More likely.
Wonderful.
See you guys all sense
this in your bones.
It's great.
This is going to be so easy.
For all of you.
All right.
We've got to keep going until
we figure out with this die.
You, you love to participate.
Come on.
Ready?
AUDIENCE: 3.
PROFESSOR 2: 3, oh man.
All right.
Ready?
AUDIENCE: 12.
PROFESSOR 2: Ooh.
Now what happened?
It's a 12-sided die?
But it could be a
20-sided die, right?
All right, let me just do a few
more, I'll tell you it I get.
I get 1, I get 10, I get 10,
I get 12, I get 3, I get 10.
All right.
Who wants to bet?
What would you be
willing to bet?
Suppose I was willing to
give you like, I don't know,
10 to 1 odds that
it's a 20-sided die.
I mean, of course,
maybe I know something.
I can see the die.
Right, so what we
want to be able to do
is precisely answer
that question.
All right, and it's just
through this Bayesian Updating.
It's not so hard, but organizing
your work is really important.
So, all right.
It was the 12-sided after all.
So you all did good.
All right, so this is
the first board question.
All right.
I want to practice making
the table Jerry showed you.
Make one for if it were 13.
Make one if I had
rolled 5 instead.
Or do the same question
if I had rolled a 9.
In each case, compute the
posterior probabilities
of each of the 5 types of dice.
PROFESSOR: You knew
it was a 20-sided die?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
PROFESSOR: All right,
what about if it's a 5?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
PROFESSOR: But that's it.
But you see how that captures
it very nicely in a table.
All of your intuition.
You knew it was a--
PROFESSOR 2: So right now you're
doing the D equals 13 case?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, or I guess
we could combine the tables.
PROFESSOR 2: Oh, I'm sorry.
You're not combining tables.
This is your
likelihood column here?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
PROFESSOR 2: And then this is
your unnormalized posterior
column.
Is that right?
Or, no this is
actually normalized.
AUDIENCE: This is for if
it were like any number.
Like if we didn't know
what number it was.
PROFESSOR 2: The likelihood?
AUDIENCE: Yes.
PROFESSOR 2: Absolutely.
So the likelihood
doesn't depend on-- wait.
What are we doing?
Rolling a 5 or a 13?
AUDIENCE: Rolling a 13, right?
PROFESSOR 2: Right,
so rolling a 13,
for the likelihood
you're computing
the probability of
data that you saw,
the 13, given the hypothesis
say that it's the 4-sided die.
AUDIENCE: Right.
PROFESSOR 2: It's
the 4-sided die,
what's the probability
you would roll a 13?
AUDIENCE: 0.
PROFESSOR 2: Great.
Same with this, this and this.
But what about here?
If it's the 20-sided die, if
that's your hypothesis, what's
the probability you'd roll a 13.
AUDIENCE: Oh no.
Oh 1/20.
PROFESSOR 2: Exactly.
So that's the likelihood column.
So this we're going to erase.
OK.
AUDIENCE 2: Then we multiply
this by this and get that.
PROFESSOR 2: Exactly.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
divide by [INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR 2: Exactly, exactly.
Does that make sense?
AUDIENCE: Wait, we
multiply these together--
AUDIENCE 2: Multiply
those three together.
And then we divide 1 over
100, so it's going to be 0--
PROFESSOR 2: So, yeah
so you get to just--
AUDIENCE: And then HD.
PROFESSOR 2: No, no.
Oh yeah, you're right.
HD.
One thing I want to point out
is instead of using a comma,
all right, this is
conditional probability
so it's probability of
D given H, like this.
OK.
There you go.
So that's absolutely right.
At the end, we want to
know how likely each
die was given the data.
AUDIENCE: Because
this total is just P.
PROFESSOR 2: That's right.
Which is 1 over 100.
Great.
So now, do it again.
Yeah, exactly.
You don't even need
to make a new table.
PROFESSOR 2: Awesome
AUDIENCE: So this
column [INAUDIBLE]
to the probability,
because [INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR 2: Yeah, you take each
hypothesis times probability
of data given that
process, which
is the same as the
probability of D and H.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, exactly.
PROFESSOR 2: So your
partitioning it up,
sort of based on hypotheses.
AUDIENCE: Because this equals
that times probability of D.
PROFESSOR 2: That's right.
AUDIENCE: D confuses me.
What is P of D?
PROFESSOR 2:
Probability of the data.
So, right so a priori, you don't
know which die it is, right?
But there's still a
probability of getting a 13.
Right?
And what is the probability?
Well first, we would
have to, in this case,
we could only pick
the 20-sided die,
that has a 1/5
chance of happening.
And then, given that we
picked the 20-sided die,
we have to roll a 13,
which is a 1/20 chance.
Which is exactly why
this sums to 100.
And then more
generally, you have
the Law of Total Probability.
So here, I think you should
keep in mind, which is the D
and which is H.
Maybe write it above,
otherwise it's a little
confusing to know what-- great.
OK, and so these are
the final probabilities
you got if you rolled a 9.
Is that right?
So there's something
off here right?
AUDIENCE: Sorry,
these are our priors.
I'm not labeling this.
These are priors.
This is gonna be [INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR 2: So actually here,
I think you have likelihood.
This is likelihood
here, exactly.
That's likelihood.
Your prior should be what?
AUDIENCE: 0.2.
PROFESSOR 2: What should it be?
AUDIENCE: 0.2 for each one.
PROFESSOR 2: Yeah, 1/5.
Oh, I didn't see the points.
Yeah, so that's your
prior, 1/5 for each.
This is your likelihood.
Then you multiply
them, and that's
the unnormalized
posterior, right?
Let's have a brief
discussion about it,
and then we're going
to give you something
a little more challenging.
So for rolling a 13, right,
the first thing you do
is ask, what is the prior?
And you saw, I had 5 dice.
I shook it around.
A student reached in
randomly, not even me.
So we can trust that
it was 1/5 each die.
Equally likely, that's a
uniform prior, right, discrete
probability mass function.
Great.
Likelihood.
Well, that's going to
depend on data, because it's
the probability of the
data given the hypotheses.
The hypothesis in this case
is how many sides on the die.
So, if the data's 13, what's the
probability that I would roll
that data, a 13, given that
it was the 4-sided die.
0.
Right, it's impossible.
Similarly 4, 6, 8 and 12 sides.
But given that I had
the 20-sided die,
there would be a 1/20
probability of rolling a 13.
That's the likelihood column.
All right.
The next column, what we called
the unnormalized posterior, we
multiply, everything is 0,
and then we get 1 out of 100
as the product for
the 20-sided die.
If we sum this up by the
Law of Total Probability,
we get the probability
of the data.
Now, a student asked,
what does that mean?
We don't know which die it was?
In this case, what
it means is that it's
reasonable to ask the question,
well, if someone reaches in,
grabs 1 of these 5 dice
randomly and rolls it
and gets-- I mean,
what's the probability
that the result would be a 13.
Right?
That's a reasonable question.
And in this case, it's not so
hard to analyze that directly,
because the only way
that could happen
is if they think the 20-sided
die and then rolled a 13.
Well, given that they
picked the 20-sided die.
Well, there's a 1/5 chance
they picked the 20-sided die,
and then a 1/20
chance they roll of 13
given that they picked
the 20-sided die.
So the probability of rolling
a 13 overall is 1 in 100.
The probability of the data.
PROFESSOR: John, let
me just say one thing.
The way we would have
done this before is you
would have made a tree.
The top branch of
the tree would have
gone to the 5 types of die,
and then each of those die
would have gone to
all the possibilities.
And the only branch
that leads to a 13
is down to the 20-sided die
and then down to the 13.
PROFESSOR 2: Notice
also that this
would be a very big tree, right?
You have 5 branches, and
then this would have 4 and 6,
and 8, and 12, and
20 coming off of it.
Finally we normalize.
Using Bayes Rule, this gives
us a posterior probability mass
function.
It's for everything but
the 20-sided hypothesis.
Therefore, we get 100%
belief, 100% probability
given that we rolled a 13,
that it was a 20-sided die.
Now of course you all
knew that immediately.
If you roll a 13, it has
to be the 20-sided die.
So let's look at a more
interesting one that you did,
the 5.
So what changes?
That's the big question.
The only thing that
changes is the likelihood.
I mean, granted
the rest changes.
But everything these
two columns are
computed from the first two.
The prior stays the same,
but the likelihood function
changes because we
have different data.
In this case, if we
roll a 5, we can't
get that on the 4-sided die.
We have a 1/6 chance on the
6-sided, 1/8 on the 8-sided,
1/12 on the 12-sided and
1/20 on the 20-sided.
Multiply those columns, get
the unnormalize probability,
or the unnormalized posterior.
That sums to the
probability of getting a 5.
When you divide by it
normalizes the posterior,
and what do we see?
Well, of course you couldn't
have used the 4-sided die,
and of the remaining the most
likely, the most probable,
given the data, is
the 6-sided die.
It has a probability,
that hypothesis
has a probability of
about 40%, compared
to the 20-sided die,
which is only about 12%.
OK.
Last one.
So this is the same deal.
Again, the likelihood
function changes.
The prior's the same.
We go through the table.
The only two possibilities
are the 12 and 20-sided,
and the 12-sided, given
that you rolled a 9,
is about twice as likely
as the 20-sided, which
should fit with your intuition.
OK.
So next, we want you to
not erase, but go back
to the boards
you've already made,
and we're going to explore a
little bit the idea of repeated
trials.
Right?
Often if you're collecting
data, you don't just
collect one data
point, you collect
a series of data
points, maybe a series
of patients in a clinical trial.
You have data coming in, right?
And you can update.
You can update each
time you get more data.
And when you do this, your
prior becomes a posterior
on the first update, and
then you use that posterior
as the prior for
the next update.
Your beliefs are being
updated as more data comes in.
If you think about it, like when
you walk outside this course,
if you're like me
you'll sort of suddenly
realize you're doing
this process all the time
in your life, and you'll start
approaching problems this way.
And if you really
like me, you'll
change your religion on
Facebook to Bayesian.
But you have to be that extreme.
So great.
So here what we want you to do
is pretend that I roll the die
and then got a 5.
And then I rolled the same
die, I didn't get a different.
I just rolled the
same die, just like I
did in that demonstration,
and then I got a 9.
OK, so now we have a sequence
of two pieces of data, 5 and 9.
So I want to find the posterior
that-- update in two steps.
I'm doing this one.
I'm doing this one!
OK, so let me show you how to
do this, and then you'll do it.
OK, so first we're going
to update for the 5.
Then we're going to
update again for the 9.
Magic!
The prior, 1/5 for each, right?
That's where we're
starting from.
We roll a 5.
That's our likelihood.
Again, you get a
0 for the 4-sided
and you get 1 over n for
each of the other n-sided
possibilities.
We multiply.
That gives us our
unnormalized posterior
for the first piece of data.
Great.
Now that is going
to be our new prior.
Now, you may complain,
wait a minute.
This doesn't add to 1.
But it's OK, because we're
going to do it again.
At the very end we'll normalize,
and we'll get the same answer
as if we had normalized here
and then normalized again.
Because we're just
multiplying the whole column
by the same scalar, by
the same real number.
OK?
So it saves you
work to not bother
to normalize the first time.
Great.
So that's our new prior.
We get our next
piece of data, the 9.
We have 0, 0, 0, 1/12 and
1/20 as the likelihood.
We multiply this new
prior by this likelihood,
get the new
unnormalized posterior.
It only has two possible
nonzero probabilities in it.
The sum, the total probability
of rolling a 5 and then a 9
is only 0.0019, OK?
PROFESSOR: That's [INAUDIBLE]
unnormalized [INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR 2: Ah!
Jerry caught me.
I was hoping a student
would catch me.
OK, maybe not.
Maybe I was fooling myself.
We haven't normalized.
So, it's not quite right.
If we had normalized here, then
by the time we got to here,
we could interpret this
as that total probability.
But in any case, the
point is we can normalize
to get to the final stage,
this final posterior,
by dividing by the sum here.
Now it adds to 1, and
at the end of the day,
what do we conclude?
We conclude that it's almost
three times more likely
that it was the 12-sided
die than that it
was the 20-sided die.
Right?
So this is very similar to
what happened when randomly
had the 12-sided and rolled it.
After two times, I had data
that looked a lot like this,
and if we had rigorously
computed those probabilities,
this is what we
would have gotten.
OK?
So now, now it's your turn.
So, we want to try the same
thing, but in the other order.
Suppose I first roll the
9 and then I roll the 5.
So that's the first question.
The second question is,
can you do it in one go?
Instead of doing it updating
for the 9 and then for the 5,
can you incorporate
both the 9 and the 5
into a single
likelihood function
and do the updating in one step?
All right, so try these and
think about what's similar,
what's different
than what I just did.
You don't have to.
You could normalize
it, then you would
multiply by the likelihood.
You'd get something
again unnormalized,
and then you'd have
normalize again,
and then you'd get
to your final answer.
Or, don't bother
normalizing at this stage.
Just multiply this by the
likelihood, and then just only
normalize once at the very end.
And you'll get the same
answer because, you know,
normalizing once and
then normalizing again
is the same as just
normalizing at the very end.
You're just multiplying
a vector, this column,
by rescaling it to
make it unit length--
AUDIENCE: And then
you're multiplying it
by something else--
PROFESSOR 2: Exactly.
Exactly.
AUDIENCE: Isn't
number 1 going to be
the same answer as the
example we just did,
because you're going to
be updating-- I mean,
it's going different.
OK, we just have to do it.
PROFESSOR 2: Absolutely.
So, yes, absolutely.
All of these could give
you the same answer
because it's the same
exact data, right?
Starting from the same priors.
But what we want
you to really see
is how the math proves that.
AUDIENCE: I mean we're just
multiplying in different order.
PROFESSOR 2: That's right.
So it all comes down to what?
What property of multiplication?
AUDIENCE: Associative?
AUDIENCE: Commutative.
PROFESSOR 2: Commutative.
I guess you're also
using associativity.
It's just that multiplication
is commutative, right?
So it doesn't matter what order
you multiply these columns in,
the final result's
going to be the same.
So just about how the
order changes depending
on the order of the 5
versus the 9, and also,
what happens if you
think of both at once,
how would you then make a
table directly for that?
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: 5.
Oh, I see.
So you multiplied-- here,
is this your likelihood?
So you multiplied that.
Where's your plus times this?
Oh, you even normalized.
Right.
So did you understand
John's statement
that you didn't actually
have to normalize?
AUDIENCE: Right.
I mean, if you'd
already done it.
PROFESSOR: No, I understand.
It's a nicer number than 1/60.
But if you didn't
have it, you could
have just used this column
and normalized at the end.
That make sense?
Excellent.
I'm not trying to--
AUDIENCE: This is just
if you do it in one step.
PROFESSOR: I see.
AUDIENCE: You just multiply.
PROFESSOR: Did you
get different answers?
AUDIENCE: No, it's the same.
PROFESSOR: It's the same.
It makes sense.
You have the data.
That's the evidence you have.
Right.
So was this all clear?
Was John's statement
about not only
needing the
unnormalized posterior
in the middle reasonably clear?
AUDIENCE: What were
talking about is
if you were to use
the normalized one,
would then your
unnormalized posterior
be the actual probabilities?
PROFESSOR: No.
No, because in order to use
the Law of Total Probability,
you have to multiply
your likelihood
by genuine probabilities.
And the unnormalized posterior
is not a genuine probability.
AUDIENCE: But if you
use the normalized one.
PROFESSOR: If you used
the normalized one,
then it would be-- that would be
the total probability of that.
That's exactly right.
AUDIENCE: But, in
this case, it's
this that's the total
probability, right?
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
This is now your
posterior probability.
These are now the probability.
So, make a distinction.
The total probability
is about the data,
and these probabilities here
are about the hypotheses.
AUDIENCE: Sort of like the fit
of the hypothesis to the data.
PROFESSOR: You
could think of that.
They're genuine probabilities.
This is the probability
that you chose
the 12-sided die given the data.
That is, if I did this a
million times and every time,
I only looked at the times
I rolled a 9 and then the 5,
you would find this
fraction of those times
would be-- it
would be a 12-sided
and this fraction
would be a 20-sided.
So, I forget what the
numbers were, like 3 to 1.
Yeah.
Makes sense?
Excellent.
AUDIENCE: So we multiply
them together, but then--
PROFESSOR 2: You get the
same exact answer, right?
AUDIENCE: So we get
these, this answer.
AUDIENCE 2: That's right,
so it's unnormalized.
PROFESSOR: And
then you normalize
it and you get this, right.
AUDIENCE: There's no way
to normalize it without--
PROFESSOR 2: All right,
let's come back together
and take a look at
what happened here.
I saw some aha moments.
That was great.
Some people cited The
Commutative Property
of Multiplication.
That made me very happy.
So, what do we do?
So when we do the
9 and then the 5,
it looks just like what I
did with the 5 and the 9,
except the likelihood
columns are flipped.
So we have our prior,
the likelihood for the 9
gives us this column.
The product gives us an,
first, unnormalized posterior.
Then we do the likelihood
for rolling a 5.
The product of the
unnormalized posterior
and the second
likelihood gives us
our final unnormalized
posterior.
And notice the sum is still
exactly what it was before,
0.019.
When we normalize, we get
exactly the same answer
that we had before.
Now, if you contrast
this with the table
we looked at when we
did the 5 and then
the 9, what changed is these
two columns were flipped around.
And so I suppose this
column was different
and this column was
different as a result.
And then the final result,
however, was exactly the same.
Now, what if we do
them both at once?
What should that mean?
If we do them both
at once then, well we
start from the
same uniform prior,
and our likelihood-- now,
we should think of the data
as both rolls, the 5 and the 9.
OK.
Now what's important
here is that if we
condition on a given hypothesis.
For example, if we
condition on the hypothesis
that it's a 12-sided
die, then the first roll
and the second roll are
independent events, right?
It means that we can figure
out the probability of a 5
and the 9 on the 12-sided die.
It's just the product
of the probability
of a 5 and a 12-sided die
and the probability of a 9
on a 12-sided die.
That's why we're justified
in taking the product.
If we condition on the die
that it is, on the hypothesis,
12-sided, then the rolls are
all independent of each other.
In particular, we get 1/12
times 1/12 for rolling a 5
and then rolling a 9.
And for the 20-sided die,
we get 1/20 times 1/20.
So now in one step, we update.
Same exact sum, we
normalize, same exact answer.
And I mentioned that some
groups, maybe when slightly
prompted by me, said oh,
multiplication is commutative.
Right?
That's all that's going on here.
In the end, all
we're doing is taking
our prior, the first likelihood
column, the second likelihood
column, multiplying them
together and then normalizing
it.
Right?
It doesn't matter what order
those likelihood columns
are in.
It doesn't matter if we think of
the 5 in the 9, the 9 in the 5,
or the 5 and 9
multiplied together
to make their own
likelihood column.
You get the same exact
unnormalized result no matter
what.
OK.
So this is all there is
to why it doesn't matter
what order you update
the data in sequentially,
it just matters
what the data is.
Now I also had a question.
Why if you could do
it all once would
you even bother with doing it
once and then doing it again?
It's a very good question.
Does anyone want to
suggest a reason?
Maybe other than
the group that I
talked to specifically
about it Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Well,
I'm just thinking,
as you're saying, if you
have ongoing patients
and you have to like
continuously update,
then the first
data set may be all
that you have at that
moment, but then you
have to keeping adding on to it.
PROFESSOR 2: That's
exactly right.
That's exactly right.
So, in life and in
clinical trials,
you don't get all the
data necessarily at once.
It sort of comes
in continuously.
When I wake up in
the morning, I don't
know what temperature
it is outside.
I have a prior, based
on what temperature
it was yesterday at
about the same time,
like I have a memory of that.
So it gives me some
prior distribution
on the temperature.
OK, that might be a continuous
one, like maybe a bell curve.
We're going to get to that next
week, these continuous updating
problems.
OK.
And then, when I
get out of bed, I
see that the window is
covered in condensation.
That's some data.
I can update my beliefs.
Probably means
it's kind of cold.
Great.
Then I can open the
window to let the cat out,
and a burst of freezing
cold air comes in,
like it did this morning--
well, actually not this morning.
This morning was great.
Yesterday it was cold.
And again, now I have more
data and I update my beliefs.
All right.
You can go through
life this way.
It'll give you a headache,
but you can do it.
Now with clinical trials,
the same thing can happen.
Maybe you do a pilot study.
Maybe you have some
belief that eating almonds
causes something,
stomach cramps.
Great.
And maybe it's just for you.
But you want to do
a study about that.
So maybe you know for yourself
that eating almonds give you
stomach cramps.
You're at the Harvard
School of Public Health
and you really want to
investigate this further,
so you gather a few
willing subjects,
you feed them some
almonds, you see
if they get stomach
cramps, how many of them.
And maybe your prior
ahead was you just kind of
felt like you had this
really strong belief that
almonds cause stomach
cramps, because it
does for you and you
really haven't even
asked a lot of other people.
So you might have a lot
of prior probability
on that hypothesis being true.
Once you collect
a few more people
and maybe you ask your
friends, maybe you
find that most of them
don't have the same problem.
Suddenly your posterior
belief changes
and now you're not quite so
convinced that it's true.
And then, if you're
really ambitious
and you have a lot of
grant money from the NIH,
you recruit 1,000
people and you do
a randomized controlled
trial with placebo
and you find out that
exactly 10% of the folks
complain about the stomach
cramps with almonds.
Maybe 10% on placebo
also, so you're
not quite sure what's going on.
But the point is,
you're getting data
a little more, a little more.
And you can keep incorporating
it, updating your beliefs.
So that's the principal.
One last thing
I'll point out is,
what if you have a
prior belief that
is so strong, so you are
so sure, for example,
that almonds don't
cause stomach pain,
because it doesn't for you
and you're just sure that that
would be ridiculous, right?
So you've put your
prior probability at 0.
How much evidence
will it take, how much
data will take for
you to be convinced?
Infinite.
No amount of data it's going
to convince you otherwise.
This is why whenever you do
this kind of Bayesian Updating,
it's generally best to leave
a little bit of possibility
for Santa Claus, OK.
Like a little bit.
Just so that should a fat white
man come down your chimney
and deliver the
presents one year,
you have a
possibility to adjust.
So those are some
things to keep in mind.
I think we've got one
more board question
that Jerry's going to lead.
PROFESSOR: Right so it's
nice to get probabilities
for hypotheses, but one
thing you also want to do
is predict what's
going to come next.
And so that's what we call
probabilistic prediction.
If I pick one of the John's 5
die, and I'm about to roll it,
you could tell me using the
Law of Total Probability
the probability that I get a 5.
And we've done that, we
did that in the first unit
on probability in this class.
But suppose he rolls a 5 first.
Now I can update my
probabilities for which
die it is, which
is going to update
my estimation of the
probability of rolling, say a 4
on the next roll.
This is what we'll call
probabilistic prediction.
We can predict what's
going to happen next,
at least with probabilities,
based on the data
that we've seen.
We update our predictions
based on that.
So here's a set up.
D1 is the first roll.
D2 is the second.
I'll do this example.
Oh no, this a board question.
You're going to do this.
You're on your own here.
So first, you
don't know anything
about the die except that 1
of the 5 was chosen at random.
What's the probability that
the first roll will be a 5?
Now you've rolled that once,
and you're going to roll again.
And you can ask, well
now I've seen some data.
I have some information
about which die was chosen.
What's the probability that
I'll see a 4 on the next die.
So that's your job to find
that for this problem.
PROFESSOR 2: Cool, alright
so this is your first answer?
AUDIENCE: Right.
And then, now we're
just multiplying across.
You get 0.
1/180, 1/320,
1/740, [INAUDIBLE].
And then add those up.
PROFESSOR 2: Yeah, get
out your calculator.
What are you dividing
by to normalize?
AUDIENCE: Is this--
I don't know.
PROFESSOR 2: That's right.
So this is, when you add these
up, exactly the probability
of the 5, right?
So now if you want to
repeat this process,
you need to use your
normalized posterior instead
of the original prior.
AUDIENCE: That's what we were--
PROFESSOR 2: Yeah.
Great.
Now, you just need
to do division.
That I can't help you with.
Calculator.
Division skills, either way.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Now this is
the probability of 4,
or the probability
of 4 getting 5?
PROFESSOR 2: That's right.
So tell me what you
did to get these.
AUDIENCE: So this
column [INAUDIBLE]
which we calculated for,
and then you sum it up
to get the total
probability of getting a 5.
And then [INAUDIBLE]
normalized it,
and then took the new
[INAUDIBLE] times the same--
PROFESSOR 2: The
same likelihood.
AUDIENCE: And then
you get the new column
and then you add it up.
[INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR 2: Perfect.
Now you said, just for the
heck of it you normalized it,
but it's actually really
important that you normalize
it, because if you're going to
use the Law of Total Probably
again, right, you've got to be
working with a probability mass
function, something
that adds to 1 here.
If you didn't normalize,
then your final answer
would get multiplied
by something, right?
Whatever that
normalization constant was,
or its reciprocal.
Perfect.
Check these guys out.
PROFESSOR: And this right
here is not a probability,
because it's unnormalized.
So what should you
normalize this by?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
In other words, if you made a
normalized probability here,
it would be this divided by
that, this divided by that.
AUDIENCE: So all we need
to do is divide this--
PROFESSOR: Exactly right.
PROFESSOR 2: How's it going?
AUDIENCE: It's going fine.
So we're just saying--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR 2: So, what
did you get for this?
How did you find it?
So you summed up this, right?
Great, and then what
did you do next?
AUDIENCE: We do the
same thing for 4.
PROFESSOR 2: So,
starting from scratch.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, starting
from scratch if you roll a 4.
AUDIENCE: OK.
So how does that
incorporated the fact
that you first rolled a 5?
AUDIENCE: So we're trying to
go back to the original Bayes,
but that didn't work
out so well because we
don't know how to
calculate this.
PROFESSOR 2: Exactly, all right.
So this is no easier than that.
So here's the idea: so you
start with this belief, right?
And you have your likelihood.
You multiply them, Law
of Total Probability,
and you get the
probability of rolling a 5.
Now at that point, after
you've rolled this 5,
your beliefs have
changed based on that
about the probability that
you have each of the 5 dice.
So if we take that and
you use that as your prior
here, then the likelihood,
multiply and sum,
that should give you--
AUDIENCE: I like that.
PROFESSOR 2: OK?
AUDIENCE: Oh, but
now we have decimals.
AUDIENCE: Now you have decimals.
I can't make your life too easy.
AUDIENCE: Use these.
PROFESSOR: Right, so
you multiply this number
by this, this number by this.
So in the end, you'll
get all of these numbers
except they're all
multiplied by, divided by.
So you should divide this
by-- to get a probability.
That make sense?
So you have to be careful for
figuring out probabilities
of hypotheses, we can avoid
using the unnormalized.
We don't have to
keep normalizing.
But when you want to do
posterior prediction,
you want real
probabilities of data.
So you're going to
have to normalize
these numbers at some point.
Either first or at the end.
It's probably, if you're
going to do it a lot,
easier to just keep doing it.
AUDIENCE: OK, Thanks.
AUDIENCE: How are we doing?
PROFESSOR: You tell me.
It's a beautiful use of color.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
PROFESSOR: So is this
normalized or not normalized?
AUDIENCE: This is normalized.
PROFESSOR: Normalized.
Good, because you are
real probabilities there.
Yes, thank you.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
AUDIENCE: And so
then we multiply
by what are the likelihoods.
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR: And now you're
going to sum it up.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
PROFESSOR: That's perfect.
AUDIENCE: Way to go Caitlin!
PROFESSOR: Because
the Law of Total
Probabilities says
multiply this by this.
That's just what you
did with the trees,
do you see the trees
when I wave my hands?
Beautiful.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
AUDIENCE: Our new prior is
given the data we had before.
PROFESSOR: Yes.
That's good.
PROFESSOR 2: You're
adding them up?
OK, so that looks right.
So let's think, how
does this number
compare to what you
would have, if you
didn't know this
other information?
So suppose you knew
nothing going in,
do you think that the fact that
you rolled a 5 the first time
makes it more or
less likely that you
roll a 4 the second time.
AUDIENCE: It should
be less likely.
PROFESSOR 2: Is it less likely?
AUDIENCE: Because you
get rid of the 4--
the die has only 4 sides.
PROFESSOR 2: So it might
make you go down, right?
On the other hand, you're
going to give more probability
to the 6-sided, let's say
that, than it had originally.
So they're sort of
competing forces.
So I'm actually not sure.
I'm not actually sure
which is the right answer.
But anyway, it's something you
can easily check or compute.
PROFESSOR: This
is a standard day.
We always finish ahead of time.
I don't need that right here.
Like with all the other
answers today, we'll
use the screens
to show the table.
So when we go through it, we do
the usual thing we did before.
We started with a 5, so we'll
update our probabilities
of the hypotheses
based on that 5.
So that's the first
column is the prior, then
the likelihood of
getting a 5, which is 0
if you have the 4-sided die:
1/6, 1/8, 1/12 and 1/20.
We get our
unnormalized posterior.
And then in this
table, I actually
got the normalized
posterior, because when
you're computing
predictive probabilities,
you need to use
normalized probabilities.
They should be
true probabilities.
So we use this column here
of the posterior probability.
There's different orders you
could do this calculation.
I think this is one of
the straightforward ones.
Then we look at the likelihood
of D2 in the next column.
Now I put a star for
H4 because there's
no way you could get
a probability there
if you have D1 and D2.
If I had left off the
D1, which most people did
and which is OK because
of the independence
John talked about,
given the hypothesis
the rolls are
independent, I would
have had a 1/4 where
I have the star.
But I'm going to multiply it
by 0 anyway, so who cares.
So I have my new
priors-- excuse me,
my new likelihoods for the
second bit of data, which
are the same as the old
ones: 1/6, 1/8, 1/12, 1/20.
Now my total probability
is done the same way.
You multiply in this
new language posterior
1, which is your prior
for likelihood 2,
times likelihood 2 and sum them
up, and I get this last column.
So again, once I have
my new, my posterior
for the first bit
of data, I can use
that in the Law of
Total Probability
to make a prediction.
So what's happened right here?
What's become more likely?
This 0.124 seems a
little bit larger
than I would have
guessed ahead of time.
What's happened with
rolling a 5 and then a 4
to make that a
little bit bigger?
Any ideas?
AUDIENCE: When you
roll a 5 first,
it increases the
probability that it's
one of the lower dice.
PROFESSOR: Excellent.
AUDIENCE: So then it
makes it more likely
that you'll get a 4.
PROFESSOR: Excellent.
That's what I would think too.
Seeing a 5-- a 4,
what did roll first?
The 5-- makes the
smaller die more likely.
If the smaller die
is more likely,
then you're more likely
to roll a 4 and a 5.
For instance, if I
had the 6-sided die,
what's the probability
I'd roll a 4 and a 5
with the 6-sided die?
1 in 36 which is about 3%.
So this doesn't get
up to 3%, but it's
a little bigger than
if I had the 20-sided
die where would
be-- what's 1/400.
PROFESSOR 2: Very small.
PROFESSOR: Small,
John says it's small.
PROFESSOR 2: So, this is one
argument you can make, right?
That ruling the 5 makes it
likely that it's a smaller die,
and therefore more
likely to roll a 4 next.
But is there another
argue that you
can make for why
maybe rolling the 5
would have the opposite effect?
It might make it less
likely to roll a 4 next?
AUDIENCE: My initial
thought was if you roll a 5,
you know it's not
the 4-sided die.
And that's your die that
you're most likely to roll for.
PROFESSOR 2: That's right.
So I'm not as sure as you as to
whether this goes up or down.
I think there are two
competing arguments.
That on the one hand,
it makes it more likely
it's a 6 or 8-sided, but it also
makes it completely impossible
that it's a 4-sided.
PROFESSOR: I'll give you 3
to 1 odds that it goes up.
PROFESSOR 2: Aw crap.
PROFESSOR: So what
he doesn't know
is whether I've
computed already or not.
PROFESSOR 2: He probably has.
But he probably did it at like
3 AM, so I don't trust it.
PROFESSOR: I simulated
it in [INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR 2: I see.
Are there any questions?
That's what we have
for today, so are there
any questions about
Bayseian Updating
or doing these computations?
All right, great.